Hathaway, Katharine Butler, 1890-1942. Papers of Katharine Butler Hathaway, 1911-1956: A Finding Aid
Papers of Katharine Butler Hathaway, 1911-1956
SC 2
Radcliffe College Archives, Schlesinger Library, Radcliffe Institute
Katharine Butler Hathaway, 1890-1942
3 file boxes
Short stories, poems, novellas, journals, class notebooks, correspondence, etc., of Katherine Butler Hathaway, Radcliffe College Class of 1914.
Accession number: R74-8
The papers of Katharine Butler Hathaway were deposited with the Radcliffe College Archives by Mrs. Theodore Frothingham in December, 1974.
BIOGRAPHY
Katharine Butler Hathaway, writer, was born in 1890 in Baltimore, Maryland. She spent her childhood in Salem, Massachusetts where she suffered tuberculosis of the spine and had to lie flat on her back for ten years. Her education consisted of one year at Abbot Academy, Andover and another year at Miss McClintock's School, Boston. KBH entered Radcliffe in the fall of 1910 as a special student. She attended Radcliffe from 1910 to 1912 and although she did not graduate, she was made a member of the class of 1914. She married Daniel Rugg Hathaway in 1932, lived at Blue Hill, Maine and died in 1942. Her husband died in 1944. She wrote autobiographical works, children's stories and poems. Her published works include Mr. Muffet's Cat and Her Trip to Paris (New York, 1934), The Little Locksmith (New York, 1943), and The Journals and Letters of The Little Locksmith (New York, 1946).
For a more detailed biography of KBH, see Radcliffe College Alumnae: Memorial Biographies, Vol. II. For college poems see Radcliffe Magazine, 1910, 1912.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
The collection consists of short stories, poems, novellas and journals. Also included are three Radcliffe class notebooks for literature courses, 1910-1913, college journals and rough drafts of Mr. Muffet's Cat and The Little Locksmith, which include a section on Radcliffe life and college friends. The collection also contains publishers' correspondence, contracts with her brother, Warren Butler, and estate documents.
CONTAINER LIST
Box 1: 1-8
Box 2: 9-20
Box 3: 21-35
INVENTORY
- "Elvira," an unpublished novel, ts., n.d. (part one)., 1.
- "Elvira," an unpublished novel, ts., n.d. (part two)., 2.
- "Elvira," an unpublished novel, ts., n.d. (part three)., 3.
- "Paradise Lost," an unpublished short story, ts., n.d., 4.
- Miscellaneous short stories: "Met in a Cottage," "The Black Pear1" (published in the Atlantic Monthly between 1915-1918), "The Fairy Husband," "Persephone's Laughter," a play, "Too tenderhearted a Story," "The Affair of Martinique," tss., mss., n.d., 5.
- "Duty and Anarchy," ms., n.d., 6.
- Mr. Muffet's Cat and her Trip to Paris, children s story, draft, ts., 7.
- "Mr. Muffet's Friends in Paris," children s story, draft, ts. c. 1932-1935., 8.
- Radcliffe class notebook for 17th and 18th century literature course, ms., 1912-1913. Journal of KBH: poems, plays, reflections, ms., 1911., 9.
- Radcliffe class notebook for 17th century literary criticism course, ts., c. 1910-1913. Radcliffe class notebook for 18th and 19th century literature course, 1913., 10.
- Account book of Daniel Rugg Hathaway, listing expenditures while in Paris 1933-1934, ms., 11.
- KBH commonplace book, ms., 1941-1942, and partial transcription of same, ts. A Report on Contraceptive Materials, pamphlet, (reprint 1941.), 12.
- KBH commonplace book and partial transcription, ms., ts., 1935., 13.
- KBH commonplace book and partial transcription, ms., ts., 1940; clipping., 14.
- KBH's journals: reminiscences, plays, poems, reflections, story ideas, ts., c. 1911-1942; ALS from Daniel Rugg Hathaway, n.d., 15.
- KBH commonplace book and partial transcription, ms., ts., n.d. "To an Ancient Head of Aphrodite," from The Atlantic Monthly, 1915., 16.
- Miscellaneous mss. of KBH, 1915-1942., 17.
- "A happy Marriage," unpublished ts., c. 1921-1932., 18.
- "Interrupted Dance," unpublished ts.; TLS from editor of The Atlantic Monthly rejecting story, 1919., 19.
- Miscellaneous notes story ideas; "Spring Evening," unpublished ts.; ALS from KBH to Thornton Wilder, 1928., 20.
- "Expense of Spirit," unpublished short story, ts., n.d., 21.
- "A Person in Love with a House," draft chapter of The Journals and Letters of the Little Locksmith, ms., n.d., 22.
- Drafts of The Little Locksmith, ms., ts., n.d., includes description of Radcliffe life and friends of KBH: Lucia Briggs, Eleanor Clement, Caroline Dudley, Catharine Huntington '11; KBH made member of class of 1914; also contributor to, and member of Radcliffe magazine board., 23.
- The Little Locksmith, notes, rough drafts, ms., n.d., 24.
- The Little Locksmith, notes, rough drafts, ms., n.d., 25.
- The Little Locksmith, notes, rough drafts, ms., n.d., 26.
- Poems and copies of poems by KBH and family, ms., ts., 1917, and n.d., 27.
- Miscellaneous notes, outlines, story ideas and sketches, ms., 1927-1941., 28.
- Miscellaneous notes, outlines, story ideas (some in French), ms., Paris, 1930s., 29.
- American expatriates and World War II, chronological outlines, ms., 1914-1942., 30.
- Correspondence with publishers and editors, ts., 1924, 1941-1942. Letter from admirer, 1944. Book of the Month club review, 1943. TLS (fragment) from KBH to Bliss Perry, 1942., 31.
- Publisher's contracts for The Little Locksmith; copy of trustee and executor agreement between Warren H. Butler (KBH's brother), and Daniel Rugg Hathaway. TLS to Warren Butler, 1943-1956., 32.
- Publisher's agreements for The Little Locksmith; TLs, accounts, 1948-1952., 33.
- Publisher's agreements for The Little Locksmith; TLs, accounts, 1950-1955., 34.
- Pen and ink illustrations for Mr. Muffet's Cat, 35.
Additional catalog entries
The following catalog entries represent persons, organizations, and topics documented in this collection. An entry for each appears in the Harvard On Line Library Information System (HOLLIS) and other automated bibliographic databases. THIS IS NOT AN INDEX.
Briggs, Lucia '09
Clement, Eleanor
Dudley, Caroline
Huntington, Catharine S. '11
Class of 1914
Diaries and Letters
Radcliffe Magazine
Student Reminiscences